and um I'm sorry I don't have the
reading done yet for number one or two
uh it's almost done for number
one uh and so you couldn't answer some
of the questions on
the uh because you needed the reading to
do that so I thought I'd give you some
of those now
um I think one tough question was the
story of Master demonstrates three
important ideas of the
worldview in general and that's just um
like if you take the fact that he ran
around town with um a s sorry my tray on
his back and no one saw my tray like he
could see my tray then that demonstrates
the what of my
tray that's emptiness okay and we love
that that's world view that's pure world
view and then uh something had to happen
in his mind before he could see my which
was Karma so you had to have new Karma
and the only way to get that much Karma
was The Compassion of trying to help the
dog so I would say karma ous compassion
to much um summarize my idea of what
worldview is and we were talking about
it with some of the students you know
almost anywhere you go in the in the
world to learn Buddhism people will talk
separately about those three ideas but
the I I think I think it's changing now
but I think there's been a thing where
people didn't tie it together you know
like they wouldn't say he couldn't see
my Traya because my Traya is empty and
he only saw my trya because he had the
karma to do that and he only got that
Karm because he was practicing
compassion I think sometimes there's a
frustration in the world among Western
GES especially that people don't Tie The
Emptiness and the karma together you
know they don't describe emptiness as
things being available to be anything
depending on what kind of com you have
you have to tie them together I think
and then compassion is the C this best
way to
light uh the other question I think that
we didn't have we didn't cover in the
class was um the two books that we'll be
using the two main commentaries one was
g j you know that called buic which is
commentary on the tant but the other one
is called uh
[Music]
Nam just to do it short
spe
[Music]
oh I have a proposal on the Sanskrit uh
anybody wouldd like to learn the
Sanskrit come an hour early on Saturday
on every Saturday and then Chris's going
to do the so it's already ready for
this and I think just might save some
time this is the the pronunciation of
the Sans and she'll have a print out so
if you can't come early on S you can get
the print out um so you know g
means apostrophe yes right here
right I should
actually you like and means a great
explanation or thorough explanation
complete explanation
of uh that was written by some people
call it an aut commentary but I think
they're wrong because at the end of the
book they say the author was one person
and the comment was
different how's
that commentary was by yeah so I used to
get confused you know like a res say
m and um so I thought there was a fight
or something about wrote it and then a
lot of Scholars said there no M you know
but at the end of the book in the Tanger
in the ancient Cannon it says this book
was written by m and it was uh sorry the
text written bya and this explanation
was written by
AR and we're going to be using that
explanation a
lot um for one reason it has a lot of s
we have this hand so it's a nice one for
me and the second reason is that g of J
bases much of his book on this common I
director so it's kind of a neat
commentary to you I think that might
cover all the weird questions or
not yeah okay sorry about that it's that
you didn't get the reading normally i'
leave a little bit out of the class and
then for you to read the reading to the
homework
question um we can uh email it even
marrow uh in the Roman you know the the
reading
we yeah people can receive that
but okay um so we're going to go on to
class
two uh which in which we cover the
subject matter of the whole book but I
thought you might like
to read What's called the g g means the
Tibetan translator before they translate
a book they always bow down to somebody
and they put that at the front of the
book you know and so there's a Gak in
the front of Arya
comment and I was reading it and I was
comparing it to the Sanskrit somebody's
bowing down in the front of the Sanskrit
version the Ancient Ancient Sanskrit
version and they're not the
same uh now we know the translator was a
pretty good guy
because uh
[Music]
transl
um he translated the root text and AR is
coming so we know he's not a dummy you
know we know the person doing the
translation was was good um
but at the beginning of the it
says which
means yeah I got down to all the
Buddhist and
bu
uh oh yeah but the Sanskrit says can you
can do
om
yeahor I bow down to
V which makes it a tant test uh maybe
but maybe he just wanted to catch the B
which is what
in which is
Diamond so it seems like the person who
wrote the Sanskrit text out had some
sort of preoccupation with d
uh also in the first verse in the
opening verse also I just point that out
to me it's interesting and why would uh
Lord AA translate it differently see and
you kind of have to know that aa's
position at n Lon Monastery was sort of
to keep the other people
straight and when uh naropa and his
friend mria had a wild s parties there
he threw out my cha for a while my cha
According to some accounts found two of
my transp I mean he was a great scholar
and a great tantri but there's this
thing where naropa claw was sort of the
um on one extreme trying to pull the
monks into a tant view and then those
who couldn't quite handle it Lord ABA
was disciplining people at the same time
and so I don't know maybe that has
something to do with his translation of
the of thees you
know but obviously the original author
was thinking about vas and he bows down
to
V then he gets in the first verse he
starts to mention
um for
[Music]
say screen I think I'm trying to make
AOL uh ge means what
Diamond those of you you all must know
but Stone and J King
Lord d means like or similar to a
diamond diamond
like number means a
vision uh a way of perceiving something
okay like Loy number means the
perception of the mind and then means
seven so we have the seven Diamond like
visions
[Music]
is the is the opening subject of this
whole book entire the opening schloka
the first verse is all devoted to the
seven Diamond Lang
diges and it all relates to what happens
when you perceive
anth uh so you're very familiar with
this I think from the diamond
cure and other things it gives me a lot
of faith to find a book where the author
is jumping right into diamonds then I
think that's a it's one indication um
that the person had
seen good it's
Good Very
we'll go through the
seven and then we'll be talking about
the seven most of the
minut paper
this okay number one
[Music]
say you
know uh Buddha so the first of the seven
Dynamite Visions
is and why that is talk about
it but I think the first thing to say is
that when you see emptiness
directly
uh when you come out of it then I think
as you know from the diamond cut then
you are aware of having met the core of
a Buddha the essential core of a Buddha
which
is the emptiness of that which is the
99% of the
dhak
so it makes sense that that would be the
first of the seven diamondite Vision y
of Jam's commentary says some of these
Visions in a way take place during the
direct receptive INF some of them take
place doing what we call the aftermath
the following hour or two hours while
you're still in meditation but you come
down out of the bre
so it's it makes sense to me that he
starts with the one
that you see during the direct you see
the
D so that gives me a a lot of faith in
my CH presentation like I believe that
it's written by someone who's at least
what level
body well both right uh my was said to
reach the 10
right the first sorry
third first and I saw B today in a text
of when did Arya
sa see emptiness directly and I believe
it was afterwards well afterwards
according to one Tex well
afterwards and I think
it yeah like maybe 10 or 20 years after
that
um just from the way he does his
commentary which he did before
that and certain indications in the
comment
um this enough
say
ch
right something is a Dharma has to be
the jeel DH
je oh yeah there was a keevin in there
and you should take care of my but
because I ended in cheer that override
so you just
say I mean just because something is the
Dharma it doesn't mean it has to be the
DU of the DH that
we show give me an example of what now
when I say give me an example I say show
me something that's Dharma but not the
Jewel of the Dharma that we got for
because those people just make them mix
them
up homework and just
com oh
sorry okay the book
yeah then I do the um Auto confirmation
what do they call it with the
tax it's a it goes back to the sender to
confirm
yeah you tell me
it's tell me it's
not why the hell
not it's
[Music]
not okay we can okay let it
go okay so it's real difficult to guess
what the thing
say
to uh in Sans it's Ghana Gana like in GH
chakra Gak
and that's the name for the C
Feast uh and there you see the idea of
many offerings brought together into a
gathering and then many people properly
initiated the Gathering and then the
office are the wheel of
off um GH chakra so that's where you see
the word g
um this is the word in tibetan the easy
word for
what
yeah and we'll get into what's real sa
and what's not real sa right we have to
debate that um but that's the third of
the seven b like Visions you have some
Vision that involves the S okay uh
number
four ch ch
say
come come has a meaning basic meaning of
a discreet cut off thing like out in
East toed there's this state this big
state of cowboys and uh the people in
central Ted kind of wish they were cut
off and they called them come
come uh when you eat food and you take a
bite that's called a K in the ancient
scripture like K means food that you
take with your mouth and bite it into
the street chunks and then Nik say is
sleep which is another kind of nutrient
Vera is the third kind of food which is
Hope and then uh concentration is the
fourth kind of food and if you don't get
all four you know like a person needs
hope and sleep and concentration to live
life
uh but K you say is edible fruit bable
fruit so K means a discret thing
category and in this text the word in
Sanskrit it means uh they shap
Nimo yeah meaning Buddha nature Buddha
nature so in this text in the Tantra
come means Buddha nature the Buddha
nature inside of you the Buddha
nature it has other names in tibetan
we'll go through them Greek is one which
is like type or family and ninbo is one
which is like heart and we'll be going
into all those different words for the
Buddha nature inside of
you um the first chapter of this book is
the longest one there are five chapters
to the utar Tantra the first chapter
treats these four of the seven Dynamite
okay so they're so important and they
hang together so well that the first
chapter is devoted to these four
together like Buddha Dharma and then the
seed for Budd inside of every person um
and they so they call that chapter
dation
shap cup which means the chapter on the
essence of the meaning the Buddha nature
and everybody so those first four are
going to be the subject of about half
the book and the debate about what it is
inside of you that becomes a Buddha and
what is the essence of a Buddha inside
of you is probably the most important
thing about this whole book so we'll be
spending a lot of time on that what is r
what is your Buddha nature and there's
so many uh weird ideas about it even in
Tibet there were very um violent debates
about it those of you who are studying
uh sa have been through a few pages of
the based on that already so from the
other guy's
Viewpoint uh number five
[Music]
that window
open sorry yeah we'll get
everybody
okay oh that's
maybe open the door okay you got to cook
I'm afraid your brain goes down but
anyway say
CH uh what's it mean check it out
Enlighten enlightened
Enlighten so naturally one of the people
in G commentary comes up and
says word it means enlightened or
enlightened
being yeah the guy comes up and G why
why mention Buddha again right actually
technically it's bod in Sanskrit instead
of Buddha but it doesn't much matter
it's still inl being you guys why do you
mention Buddha again you
know you'll find out
say
y y means good spiritual quality good
quality they can roughly be divided into
two kinds one is uh
the accomplishment of the quality of
having gotten rid of your anger for
examp that would be a y that's what we
call Char we got rid of something NE and
that's a good
qualitya s then the other one might be
that you have developed the ability to
see into all these previous
Minds uh which would be which I haven't
done uh and that would be uh naming
which means a karmic result good problem
that you have to work on as and then
something positive that you
acquire so that's
young and here it means qu is him an
enlightened being okay not just an
enlightened being
[Music]
take ch ch ch
ch it's a common Tibetan name chin doia
is one of our great
and um so chin means uh enlightened
activity of a Buddha Karma of a Buddha
in s you change
Buddha and you get Buddha is Karm
meaning activity of enlightened being
I'm going to go through these seven
again G of J immediately jumps into the
seven he's going to talk about the seven
in three different ways and we'll cover
that tonight first question is what are
they like you know what's their
nature and the answer is going to be
there's a real seven and there's a not a
real
seven okay there's a real seven and
there's a not a real seven that's uh the
first way he's going to discuss the
seven then we'll take a break for
Refreshments okay then he gets
into how come you only got seven you
might have eight or six or nine or
something like that why do it got to be
seven okay you know why does m mraa want
to say that B7 are the most important
thing of all the diamond like Vision I
mean lots of stuff happens during the
perception infinite you got 16 aspects
of the
form you know why not talk about those
20 Things No it's got to be
St uh then he says is there any logic to
the order of the stach you know why does
it go Buddha Dharma sa Buddha nature
back to Buddha Buddhist qualities
Buddhist activities you know why why do
you go in that FL why didn't you present
it like Buddha Buddha Buddhist activity
you know but why did you do to Buddhist
anyway you know but we'll get there so
those are the three things we have to
cover
and then by next week our next class
we'll be ready to go on to the first of
the diamond and see more about you know
in
detail
uh so we said there's two kinds of
Buddhas right like a real Buddha and a
not real
Buddha and those are called bam
minut
say they done they done good job good
job so I'm going to quote a
Sutra that a quotes in his commentary
okay to the utra and I tried to find out
which
Sutra uh in the database and it seems to
be one called uh the suture which
teaches
slum what's slum personal responsibility
yeah personal responsibility like I will
um tree all living beings even if nobody
helps me even if everyone fights me I'll
still do it and I'll do it with every
breath and every moment of my life I
will not give up I will not get
discouraged I will not wait for anybody
else to help me if people hassle me I'll
just keep cruising and that's called
haum okay haum so uh this comes from a
part of a scripture called the
presentation of
FX
um I the sound just for good luck okay
and maybe Chris can help you if anyone's
really interested
uh oh Anand which is the great disciple
of Lord Buddha his name means Bliss
right this
oh the Buddha is not something that
anyone could ever show you you could
never see the
Buddha
at no one could ever see the bud right
uh
uh no one can describe the Dharma okay
the Dharma is
undescribable you
can't talk the DH cannot be spoken the D
cannot
be the ears cannot hear the D okay the
ears cannot hear
the uh you never bring the
together uh and no one could ever go to
the sa and pay homage to them and make
offerings for them it's impossible so
what we got so far uh you can't see a
Buddha uh you can't hear the Dharma and
it's
unspeakable and you could never bring
the sa together and even if you did you
couldn't
offer them anything or help them or pay
H it for them okay
um and then I'll switch to Oh's do
[Music]
it which
means
um they are not something The Saga is
not something you could bow down to with
your body or with your mind
uh and these are the first three of the
diamond like Visions they're
called
okay
uh so we got a debate
right
uh what that girl in the
back
Emma thank you may nobody could show me
the Buddha
[Music]
no say say be be you got to be
like I'm saying look I can see the bra
right
hereone
canone
okay you telling me nobody can
he yeah so there's no Buddhist
I
didn't what do you mean when you
say that's pretty
good yeah good okay you can't see a
selfish what would be a good test of
that to prove that Lord Buddha or say
that his Holiness dama is not
self what would be a good
proof they
imp that's pretty
good yeah I mean I took a flight out of
Beijing and they handed me a newspaper
in English they had the D Lama's photo
right in the front it said Public Enemy
Number One you know and then they
discarded all the evil things of dama so
D is empty you know some people proceed
in one way some people proceed in the
different way that's the emptiness of
the Buddha right
um but we have to get into dund and K
Buddha okay and now I'm going to go to
to GJ the whole presentation comes out
of that Sutra GJ struggling to explain
this sura why is it you can't see the
Buddha why is it that nobody could show
you the Buddha and he says you know we
have to divide Buddha into dund means
ultimate Buddha and K means deceptive
Buddha like illusory Buddha the Buddha
that seems to be a Buddha it's not a
Buddha
okay and he goes through that pattern
for each of the seven so we'll go
through that since it's on your homework
and all that that's how I get people to
listen uh he says ultimate Buddha okay
we're going to have how many
now 14 they have the ultimate version of
the seven and the fake version of the
seven okay ultimate Buddha consists of
two things he
says which
means which has as its
nature eliminating things
and and ultimate wisdom okay though you
have to understand that the dharmakaya
of the Buddha can be divided into two
one is his omniscience or her omnition
okay the wisdom of a Buddha the ultimate
wisdom of a
Buddha but the
other is the elimination of
what yeah like mental bad qualities
obstacles TOS obstacles to omnition and
then on a very subtle level what
else we could say that or how about we
say of
self-existence okay so Buddha has
abandoned
self-existence
yeah uh and this paper has abandoned
suff so this paper has suffering
oh is it 12 in long or 14 in
Long right old old rabbit rabbit's horn
right uh yeah so in a sense when did
Lord Buddha abandon
self-existence I was good at this he did
it last time
when did Lord Buddha abandon something
you
know last last CL both these guys uh
yeah never had it so in that sense he's
abandoned that um but he's
also it is it is dakai is part
what emptiness emptiness of okay and
that emptiness comes in you know we'll
talk about it later but there's a kind
of emptiness that we all have that we've
had from the beginning right that's
attached to an impure person in my case
right that's attached to a mortal diable
being uh that's one kind of Buddha
nature but then after you become
enlightened it's attached to what to a
pure being so the emptiness doesn't
change but it attachments change it's a
cal change
so anyway that's a distinction you have
to make in the case of a Buddha the
ultimate Buddha is the
omniscience and the loss of
self-existence and the loss of bad cies
Al together called
the that's the real Buddha okay d means
that's the real Buddha when you go for
Refuge you go for Refuge to that Buddha
okay not even to the FCO or you could
say the apparent Buddha which is if I
put the dhakai over here which I put
over
here
Rupa uh sometimes we divide four bodies
sometimes three bodies and sometimes
just two bodies tonight we're doing two
bodies you're either the Buddha's
knowledge on his emptiness or her
emptiness or you are all the physical
appearances of a Buddha the latter one
is
K which means what receptive receptive
that ain't what the Buddha is all about
that's not what the Buddha is all about
the way the Buddha looks even in the
Buddhist Paradise the way Lord Buddha
looks when Lord Buddha comes to a planet
that's not what the Buddha is all about
that's not what we take refuge
in It's The Emptiness of Lord Budd and
that's the Buddha that you meet for the
first time directly when you see
emptiness
that that's the Lord Buddha
why don't forget we're not talking about
we start distinction between what and
what Buddha and
and the what of self-existence Jewel of
okay like we all started out tonight
deting between the Buddha and the Jewel
of the Buddha right as in the three
jewels right should be
walking
um and it's only the second one that can
protect you it's only the second one you
should go for
refug why can't the protect you
uh that's in one way but can you be
protected by the appearance of Lord I
mean in in an ultimate way no only if it
stirred your memory of the D yeah I mean
some yeah that's pretty good answer uh
you could debate that all night probably
in like
uh that those colors and shapes in and
of themselves can't protect
that's obvious I mean no Buddhist in
America in the new realm of Buddhism
right should ever have this thing about
worshiping the images I mean and that's
why religions throughout history have um
discouraged worship worshiping images
they can't help you they can't really
help you much less you know that's not
the rupai rupi is what your physical
bodies yeah I mean Lord Buddha walks
around on our planet Earth and our son
is saying and my TR is saying fake fake
Refuge fake Buddha can't help you can't
help you and that's a thing you know we
talked about it before Lord Buddha was
shakuni right King of the Shaka people
which means a small village Lord and uh
they were attacked one day and all the
people came in for protection and and
hung on to his robes and they were cut
down holding on to him you know can't
help you that Buddha can't help you you
don't
go and prostrate to that Buddha you
don't go and prostrate to that picture
but the dind Buddha the ultimate Buddha
can that help you yeah 20 minutes of
seeing that of emptiness you're out of
here in seven lifetimes or less okay
guaranteed and that's protection that's
refuge in Practical terms you know
you're going to teach this at the Y I'm
here right those are surv
and
um maybe a lot of those people will just
be
walking from UA or something right or
fourth and they're going to
say how are you going to explain it to
them
like I don't think you'd want to go
straight to the direct perception in
right like I heard a lot of grumbling
about that after the yoga Sutra those
Buddhists they're always talking about
direct perception of something I don't
know
uh how could you present that to someone
as protection
EMP in their real
life he L and understands where are
coming from in your world experi
from to
change
yeah I think that and to tell you the
truth most people are very interested in
how to get rid of the bad stuff you know
like the screaming boss or the
irritating friend or the the way to
Spill the coke on you right I mean most
people uh don't question reality until
they get cancer or something like that
you know they're not too interested
about the real nature of where that
bonus came from at work they're very
interested in why they got laid
off uh and so it's good to go there
sometimes you know uh that's where
people could start using D Dharma right
away whether they ever come back through
the ym the after your first class with
never okay right if they never come back
if that's all they ever
hear people are your perception the
people who upset you are the mirror of
you uh because they're empty and someone
loved them and and we get into that I
really suggest that if you watch as ho
is teach like in Central Park we listen
to the CD over and over during Retreat
like on Sunday nights and um
he says I'm going to teach the eight
versus loj you know then he gives a hour
and 20 minute talk about getting along
with each other and then in the last 10
minutes he does the last seven verses of
the if you check it out and uh a lot of
great llamas will do that you know this
is a vehicle the Tantra is a vehicle
it's an excuse to talk about Karma
emptiness and compassion and you got to
get right to it you know like say these
are the seven and by the way
you know and then start talking about
the waiter or their wife or their the
guy at work that they don't
like
okay
uh fake fake sorry real Dharma and fake
Dharma real Dharma and F I'll read you
from the sensations the truth
of the sensations and the path in the
person in a person of the Mahayana class
Mahayana family is what the real Dharma
is which
means
uh for example I'll give you an example
of the truth of sensation in the mind of
a person who's a body
s
uh when you see emptiness directly and
when you come out of it you lose
permanently two or three mental
name
anyone doubt doubt is one of the most
famous ones like you can no longer doubt
the Buddhist God and you can no longer
doubt uh the truth of emptiness you
can't doubt the books anymore at all
ever and you would spend your whole life
trying to save them actually after that
so that's an example of the truth of
sensation in the mind of a they have SA
ceased doubting forever truth of
sensation means it's a fancy word for
saying you got rid of some bad thing in
your mind permanently you won't have it
again you'll never have it again
that's so and then
L is a synonym
for which means realization okay the
truth of the path in Buddhism doesn't
have anything to do with a r or even
with a series of uh procedures for
getting in
line it's it's ideas it's raw ideas you
know we're in the idea business I often
think of that you know I went to to
Willcox people were selling air
conditioners
tacos uh french
fries uh he uh alala fertilizer you know
it's a wide variety there and
um and I thought well we're in the idea
of business you know that's what we do
you know it's kind of intangible and the
money is
[Music]
too but if you think about it we're
we're ping ideas and that's the Dharma
Refuge that's the real Dharma so for
example the direct perception of
emptiness in the mind of a is the path
is the truth of the path the truth of
the path and the truth of having stopped
certain bad things forever is the real D
is the real d
which implies that what is not the real
D yeah like books or even the teachings
even verbal teachings that's the
apparent D okay the whole collection of
all the teachings that we given on this
planet about Buddhism are fake DH
they're not the real D okay and when you
go for Refuge you go for refence to what
it's really the perception of infiny and
the good stuff that happens to your
after that you know the qualities you
start to get rid of bad qualities you
start to get rid of that's the real
[Music]
bad we got a couple more to
[Applause]
go does that mean you can
disrespect somewhere in the scripture
says that's really D well no that's a
really easy thing to think and a really
wrong thing to
should
be
um ultimate s ready ultimate
s the the degree of Liberation and
knowledge that a b SATA has who has seen
emptiness Spirit okay that's a little
different than the presentation you guys
got in earlier courses and I am my sorry
my CH is getting a little bit different
presentation here uh so I think it's
kind of useful to compare it's useful
always to have two or three different
presentations and that makes you think
about the
differences so it's the same guy is
teaching it right he's giving a slightly
different presentation here so
sa real sa is the degree of Liberation
and and knowledge that a bodh SAA who
seen emptiness directly hand that's the
real
Sun the UN is all
those the people now that's different
from the presentation you had I think in
course
two but that's why this is called an
in-depth course we're getting a little
deep it's even more so okay
uh what's the next of the seven we got
to get you all seven before we get
refreshing sorry yeah Buddha nature come
okay Buddha
nature here's the real
[Music]
nature the emptiness in the mind of
every living
being which is still involved with
impure
stuff The Emptiness in the mind of every
living
being and normally we say suffering
living being okay uh which is still
involved with impure
stuff uh hang on
[Music]
yeah I want to clarify that I forgot one
thing okay it's the emptiness of their
mind in their mind he uses to okay The
Emptiness of the Mind in the mind of
every living being The Emptiness in the
mind of the Mind in the mind of every
living being is there real good
[Music]
ultimately so
so who wants
to do a debate you want
to
[Music]
uh D come ultimate
nature
that's Buddhist don't have Buddha
nature no they do budh
[Music]
tell me Buddhist have this Cal thing
this element thing nature
thing gaman Kian they have the fake one
or the
real in the debate you're kind of like
this you're like on Michael when are you
ready real one real one already
yeah so they
have telling me they have that kind of
emptiness that all suffering being have
in their mind which is still mixed up
with imp stuff right yes
well tell me Buddhist still
have they still have they have the mind
that is they have a mind that is pure
that in ordinary things is mix with well
that's
[Music]
so they have tea and they don't have
they have City and they don't
have they don't
havei oh so you don't have nature they
do have nature but it's filed
by so they don't have the nature which
is still connected to computer exactly
well now G at this point says that
proves
it he says you guys stop thinking that
Buddhist are Buddha they don't because
Buddha nature means Buddha
se you see and it always means still
mixed up with
impurity by definition yeah Rick is
mixed up with impurity yeah okay yeah so
that's a subtle point you know that's a
subtle point when you get to buddhahood
you lose
your Buddha nature so it's just a bad
translation actually Buddha Vick should
be translated like seed rather than
okay CU you lose it when you get in
life
okay if that's the real budha nature
what do you think might be
oh if the real budha nature is
empate then what do you think might be
the apparent bu nature the fake bu
nature those of you who know to it's a
difference between R and G say
[Music]
two kinds
of me
it's it's like your emptiness your The
Emptiness of your mind it's your natural
good which which which resides in you
naturally by
nature and then
G the body and
mind yeah uh G defines it as following
[Music]
that little part of all living beings
which is their capacity to grow into
good it's their capacity to
grow which is not the same as the
availability of brood see I mean which
is their emptiness it's a difference one
is the emptiness of the dog on the side
of the road
one is the result of the karma
rening in arya's mind get the difference
the dog is available to be my because
the dog is
empty uh what makes the dog my is the
karma in AR's mind and we call that a
growable Buddha nature or uh what do you
call it what do you call when you do
crops you
rot uh
when you take care of them what you
call cultivate yeah the part of the you
the piece in you the piece of you that
can be cultivated into a Buddha is
called your cultivatable Buddha name
Cal uh there's two kinds of Comm see
okay the fake one the one that ain't the
ultimate one is the the growable one the
cultivatable one okay well then is Rick
synonymous with Comm in this case y okay
and and the other one is just the fact
that you're available for anything
because you're
empty okay which is more
powerful The Emptiness I mean that's
what makes everything public that's what
makes everything public there's even a
debate later that we're going to get
into
luckily
uh of uh how can you call that a
SE
Shen he's a mind
I got to go to
My Buddha nature is a is a cause thing
right changeable
thing but don't give me
any we're talking about the
INF the ultimate Buddha nature the fact
that you are empty you're available to
become a Buddha the dog was empty
available to become my if you got the
right seats
huh what
I nature it must be a changing thing cuz
it's the seed from which wood
grow
not you said you say I don't
agree so it is a brha seat you can have
a seat that doesn't
[Laughter]
grow yes ni
him right it's it can't be a changing
thing that thing never changes
everyone's got it it's the only thing
that saves us everyone's available it's
the
availability technically speaking is the
lack of not being
aailable okay that's not that is
the that's yeah the K is the growable
cultivatable one okay so like your mind
so the empty dog that was available to
become my tra the availability of the
dog the availability of the dog is the
dog's Kuno in A's L uh yeah
yeah okay in four right y
I's getting closer and
closer uh now we'll get to the
difference between ultimate enlightened
one and fake enlightened one okay
ultimate enlightened
[Music]
one he says same as
above number
one so now here's the answer to the big
question right
right and this you got to appreciate
it's going to help us after the
refreshment
um the first Buddha mentioned Diamond
like Vision number
one is the Buddha that you will come to
be is the Buddha that you will come to
be it's what we call result Refuge if
you remember it's result Refuge it's the
Buddha you're going to be like when
aliser prostrates to this Buddha one way
to think about it is that I'm bowing
down to the Buddha I will
become okay and that's a very important
form of Refuge it's called uh what did I
say result Refuge result refe you're
taking refuge in what result you're
going to come out
as okay that's the first Buddha
mentioned in the seven the list of the
seven now you tell me what number four
is five
yeah you can say all the other ones all
the buddist that already exist you see
they're
called causal ref why they make you
become a they're the cause for you to
become a Buddha okay so now we got a
difference between two kinds of Buddha
refes two kinds of Buddha Jews the first
Buddha that Arya M ever teaches in thear
Tantra is the one you will be
named jamb my why not everyone's going
to become my somebody triy to debate
that to me today but I guess they never
saw a pen I mean a s okay uh how many
sticks are there in this room you see
how many cylinders in this room don't
tell me you can't all be my forget that
okay then number five is all the other
buddh that are around maybe everybody
else in this room except me or you I
don't
know no anyway uh they're called causal
refe because you they are the cause of
you becoming a Buddha
why they're around you all day they piss
you off they make you happy they teach
you they outrage you
they whatever okay they do what they
have to do to get you there okay don't
think they're all like this nice smooy
guy they always have four aspects she
means what
G generous giving warm
powerful
kick okay every great Lama has to have
all four available in their toolbx
generous warm
ra gay gay means like party like T you
know party generous give money feed
people make people feel cool one uh
powerful like hisus I mean hisus walks
in the room power doc if you've ever
seen with been with K on a bad day when
you had a bad
[Music]
day you can be very uh rful so those are
the four uh part anyway what I'm saying
is that just because the people around
you aren't all sweet gentle animall
loving Sanctuary
buildering you
[Music]
know doesn't at all prove that doesn't
at all prove anything about they're
being a Buddha or not okay if they teach
you if they bring you one step further
by pissing you
off then the in the chin the activity of
Buddha has manifested in your life
that's it
okay it's one more incentive to get
light right
okay uh on to good
qualities you said were two yeah it's
going to be
two
Sor oh good qualities oh same as number
one just copy it from number
one but in the mind of another person
as opposed to in your own mind coming in
your own mind is number one already
achieved in someone else's mind is
number
five
okay uh and I always got confused
because CA to me would seem to
be me in the future and I have to cause
it now I always have to look it up on
the computer before I teach that class I
always get confused just think of it as
taking refuge in the cause which is
outside you another person who's already
inl taking refuge in the result
is taking refuge in what you will become
number five is the first number one is
the
thir so number two
[Laughter]
is
uh then ultimate ones are where the
Buddha has has
eliminated uh certain
things and thereby achieve you know we
talked about it eliminated
self-existence or
eliminated bad qualities like
ignorance and then the the apparent or
the sort of luser good qualities are
what we call the uh karmic ripening that
turn into the Buddha's good quality for
example the Buddha om
Miss again the emphasis is on
what empty the real ones are connected
with
them and the other ones are the ones
that grew see how the the real ones are
connected to your innate Buddha nature
the not so real ones are connected to
your cultivatable Buddha nature right
different thing same same
emphasis but this is a naen this is a
real naen scripture I mean he just goes
after emptiness and common he's not
interested in anything else nothing else
the whole book all your going to get is
this broken record emptiness and Karma
emptiness and Karma emptiness in karma
okay I like that kind of book that's a
real perfectional withdom book that's a
ACI book that's a real ACI book that's
what really saves
people uh last
one ultimate enlightened activity
[Music]
Chim ultimate enlightened activity is
called J jashi
means the wisdom in an enlightened
being's mind that allows them to
accomplish all their incredible de
J the wisdom in an enlightened being's
mind which allows them to do all the
need stuff think called J
and then he
says the apparent activity of Buddha is
all the teachings of of all the
teachings so the
real uh activity of Buddha is their
wisdom that allows them to do all that
incredible stuff the state of mind that
allows them to do all this stuff the
apparent uh activity of Buddha is the
stuff we see them do like
teaching the first is much more powerful
the first is the source of the
second so we still have to talk about
two things um we're going to talk about
why seven why not 6 on N or eight or n
and then we're going to talk about
uh is there any logical order to these
seven you know if there's some reason
why my TR has presented the seven in
this
particular then we'll be really familiar
with all the seven three different
viewpoints and then will go on next uh
class to the
first so have something to drink and
something to eat and come back in 10
minutes or
so do
[Music]
when G of J is trying to explain why
exactly seven and not 6 or8
here's how he starts out he starts out
with two numbers he says look the most
important thing is
to uh take care of
others in an ultimate way take care of
all this in an ultimate way to do that
you have to take
care yourself yourself
and the only person who can do both in
an ultimate Way is a
Buddha so that justifies the first of
the seven right it's only a Buddha who
can do both
things then we'll leave some space
here
[Laughter]
right leave a little empty space in your
paper I'll be back later for that
uh and then to to become a Buddha you
really have to develop what
your good in nature good in nature down
here okay
and he calls this
cause you can call it
uh material
C is this still number
one uh well this was number one up here
right right and this is already down to
number 55
right what do we mean when we say near
material cost the stuff that the stuff
that turns into the thing in the case of
a tree what's the material cause seed
seed right so if you talk about the
material cause of your own Enlightenment
it's your Buddha nature that's going to
grow into a Buddha
okay now there's a lot of debate about
that and we won't do it tonight okay we
won't do it tonight like what's your
ultimate V nature and how about
re your emptiness okay The Emptiness of
your own mind right The Emptiness of the
mind and the mind of all living be right
so does that is that can that be a cause
of
anything
yeah sh
can young
shck of yeah it's a lack of a thing it
never changes it never changes it always
stays the same it's just the fact that
you aren't what you thought you were
that's your empty never changes can't go
on to anything why call them a
ja g j gets out of it okay he says well
look we could be talking about the
cultivatable boy nature which is your
mind and your body and that's grows into
a
budh yeah gig the cultivat
the or in a way you know you could say
that on the Bottom of Everything lies
there could be what do you call
it it's like
capacity the
potential to be anything that lies below
everything it's the in a sense for
everything it's the it's the material
cause for everything and we had that in
s we had that idea that emptiness is
lying below all
cation it's the potential that lies
below all things if you read The Diamond
Cutter Business book like I didn't want
to call it emptiness in the business
books I called it the big potential you
know and
uh and that you can think of as
emptiness it lies below all
causes uh so now we get to if this is
near link you guess what this
is f chicken say F chicken chicken
taken like uh contributing
factor and we're going to cover six and
seven
right and and contributing factors they
are both contributing factors five is
the material is the stuff that turns
into a six and seven are the factors
that assist you in becoming
a in the metaphor a tree what are
they water sunlight soil soil those are
P
tickets this goes back by the way to the
idea of result refuge and cause Refuge
why Michael say again some of these are
I I would say the first three are
supposed to be what result
refug the last three are supposed to
be cause Refuge okay why
how the first three would be ultimate
and the last three would be deceptive or
a parent uh maybe you can say that but
but if I said in terms of self and
somebody
else the first three are yourself or
somebody else yourself good in the
future and the last two are myself now
uh no somebody else no who's already a
Buddha oh okay okay they're good
qualities and their activity and so what
you can just think of is that the last
two are people who are already
Buddhist the good qualities they have
and what they want to share with you the
way they talk to you they way they act
towards you like that okay activity
right enlightened
activity and then all the good qualities
that make that
[Music]
possible because they ain't what turns
into your own Buddha they ain't what
turns into Michael the Buddha you know
so many lifetimes from now whatever so
many months from now
weeks okay number five is the thing that
turns into
Michael number six and seven is what
it's like cheering him on it's like
external factors that contribute like
the soil and the water and okay did six
and seven belong to somebody else five
belongs to
you five is what in inside of you turns
into a Buddha six and seven are what's
outside of you that convinces you to
become a
Buddha
so then um
oh for is
easy it's the Buddha outside of you now
that's going to contribute also right
right okay number one was the
Buddha that you're going to become
number four was the Buddha outside you
whose whose speech and good qualities
talk you into becoming brother so that's
easy now G says
why why do you throw
in uh
Dharma how you going to fit that
in you know
it's the Buddha that you want to become
you know that's the that's the big money
this is just like uh realizations in the
head of a person who seen emptiness
directly this is just people have seen
emptiness directly how are you going to
fit them in you don't need to throw
those two in everybody complains to my
tra said look you could do with five
Diamond like Visions you don't need
seven uh it's a little tricky
but in my transcript he presents this
idea of three tracks like we know about
Buddy St the track and then there are
two lower tracks called
what
remember s Buddha is the third one I'm
sorry the second one and this is the
third one right so g j gets around and
he says
look Buddha is what bodh safas are after
you know when they when you said to a
Buddha what would to bodh what would you
like to become
future Refuge right I'd like to become
Buddha but when you talk to a self-made
Buddha track lower track people they're
called Lower track people they're mainly
interested just in getting their rear
end out of pain the pain of all all
pain so really what they're fixated on
is learning The Wheel of Life well tell
me about The Wheel of Life cuz that's
enough to get you out of SAR it's enough
to get you to be an arot an enemy
Destroyer okay that's all they're
interested in so G of J says really
number one is talking about track number
one number two is talking about people
on track number two who are going to use
the Dharma in the form of The Wheel of
Life 12 Links of depend oration to get
their rear end out of
also oh so uh then what would number
three be third
try yeah well it's basically the
listeners and then G day he says well
look when you're a listener and you're
just about to get to be an Arun in your
last life all you need is someone a
friend a companion sa to come up to you
and give you that last teaching and they
push you over the
edge so people on the third track are
really interested in s someone to give
him that last
teaching and that's how you justify the
seven that's why mraa said there were
exactly seven no more no less
okay every Buddhist office want to be
Buddhas people on the self-made Buddha
track want to get Dharma so they can get
to be an Aran people on the third track
want to get S to come up to them and
push them over that last life to be Aran
Nirvana um everybody has to depend on an
external Buddha to help them there are
two contributing causes there of their
good qualities and all the things they
do like teaching people and they you
have to cultivate that Buddha nature
inside of you so you can become in line
that's why there's
something okay second part of the horse
race it's kind of confusing when you
read the commentary we just finished
what a justification why the number is
seven that's not very important it's not
on your homework mostly just to fill in
the
class I think now we get to something
which is the order of the sun why
present them in that order okay and I
kind of like that this has a lot to do
with bodh says
gel I want to get to be a Buddha
why if I can get to be a
Buddha then I can help others in the
main way that buddh help others which is
what I mean they can't transfer their
knowledge to other people they have to
show
which is thought mean mainly mainly they
can emate as a wind up on the hill or
something but uh mainly they have to
talk and say something teach people the
Dharma okay so Dharma comes
second and G of Jo is doing it look is
this future Buddha or current
Buddha Number One future Buddhist or
current Buddhist well it's not tempic
class right
yes the Buddha we will become it's the
Buddha we will become but we want to
become a Buddha in the future so we can
teach Dharma to
people if we do a good
job all the students at diamond mountain
university for the next 100 years or
thousand years or
whatever will all be see ESS direct and
then there's the
S Okay so we've caused the SU
so the first three are are in a
sense looking ahead to your future
buddhahood and saying I can make people
see emptiness if I can teach ACI courses
correctly and to that I really should be
enlightened okay that's the like
motivation it's one half of bodh you
know
shend three years ago
was
sorry I want to get to Buddha in order
to help other and the Buddha part I
can't do unless I uh can can meet Budd
right let me check this
[Music]
oh that's a good point we didn't cover
that I want to throw something in okay
this it just happened to come up here
why do they call him like a
diamond you guys know from the diamond
col and you know the three reasons why
they like a DI who's got
one sorry yeah ultimate totally ultimate
Beyond everything diamond is the hardest
thing in the universe nothing got a
diamond except another Diamond you can
smash it you can put a laser through it
but nothing can scratch it Diamond
except in the universe closest thing to
an ultimate in our world second
reason all around you and you can't
sit every object in this room has
emptiness the T of Min has emptiness you
know uh the whole house has emptiness
its own emptiness every bug on the
ground outside has its
own third reason
equ yeah equally empty like when you
smash a diamond every piece of the
diamond every molecule of a diamond has
a perfect carbing configuration every
piece is equally Perfect all of those
emptinesses are the same the object they
attach to is different but the
emptinesses are all the same now
Arya
says these are called These are compared
to a diamond because a diamond is so
hard to pierce
okay so hard to
pierce uh and then he goes on to say the
reason being you can't really grasp
emptiness through learning or through
contemplation like the kinds of wisdom
you get in this class through
intellectual thinking and the kind of
wisdoms you get
um I'm sorry the kind of wisdom you get
when I describe ESS to you verbally the
kind of understanding you get when you
go home and think about it is not enough
to crack the nut it's not enough to
pierce the diamond you won't be able to
see that in itself cannot see empty you
have to go into a deep state of
meditation you have to do long
Retreats some day in one of those deep
Retreats probably it's going to be
difficult out Retreat right not
impossible but more difficult someday if
you have a place to go to have deep
Retreats for many people
then one of them is going to hit the
jackpot and and see emptiness directly
in a state of deep meditation if they
have those circumstances T right uh
otherwise very hard to pierce that di
that's how Aya describes the meaning of
the diamond in his commentary my TR just
says look these are all like a diamond
because they relate to what happens to a
person when they see this
directly now my question for you is a
and I at this point
no he's not the author of the commentary
we
using
uh I don't think he was an AUD at that
you know according to the books even
according to the books if you just want
to according to the
scriptures
uh he didn't attain it till later till
till after he had taught his students
for a while and apparently when he was
writing this he had not attained
I think the explanation of
diamond uh is not as cool as the diamond
C now I just thr that up you can cook it
you can cook it I think my chair had
something else in mind you know I think
my chair was talking about those three
uh I think the author of The Tantra knew
very well what the diamond meant and
that's why he starts out the book with
the diamond the first the first line is
already talking about
di anyway you can cook that uh
to get to
Buddha what's number
five oh you have to develop your Buddha
nature okay what does it mean to develop
your Buddha nature what did we say about
Good
Nature Michael was talking about it's
tainted with imperi yeah it's tainted
it's tainted so at number five you're
doing what
cleaning Buddha nature
we feeling your bu nature cleaning and
that's a huge debate about you know how
can you make emptiness more empty you
going to clean emptiness you know then
we'll we'll debate that when we get to
Budd okay uh number
six is
what yeah quality qualties
don't you have to go find somebody with
those qual you have to find somebody
with those qual and then they can talk
to
you which is their
activity and that's the logic of the
order of the seven as opposed to the
number of the seven it's a lot of it's
close but it's not quite the same I
think the logic of the order is much
more important I think the logic of the
number is sort of strange
you
know so anyway there it is okay uh I
need to become a Buddha so I can teach
the D to people so they can see
emptiness directly to do that I'm going
to have to get to someone who's already
a Buddha so that they can help me clean
up the impurities which are obscuring my
Buddha nature or and to do that they've
got to have enlightened qualities so
they can talk to me and teach me what I
need to know
that was
fast uh how are we doing here yeah
that's
good
uh that's all for tonight's
we we'll do that um the homework is
actually ready on really you're amazing
that looks more like a quiz to me it is
a qu but there's homework oh oh so they
get homework but not quiz I'm going to
give one and two
have one
already only two yeah I out one yeah so
get your homework from ell you're
responsible for both homeworks
on Saturday is it Saturday yeah um we
started
2:00 um quiz is on Saturday too quiz on
Saturday too at
2:00 um come ready to do the quiz and
don't in B on the quiz come on if you're
going to teach you're taking
responsibility for other people ly
seriously like I think a lot of people
are coming to T some like Maybe not
maybe they'll be nobody but uh on the on
the hope that people come uh you guys
got to really be ready and and you know
it's really the first uh demonstration
of diamond mountain university
teaching uh so you know you got to put
on a good show so you got to really
study hard and don't forget you have to
talk to somebody else and you know a
quiz is okay a homework is okay but
talking to someone else uh between the
class is very powerful I used to do it
by phone uh in how I you know we used to
debate by phone with friends who lived
uh in Pennsylvania or something like
that it was really expensive but uh but
that's a way to do it if you don't have
anybody um those of you who are
interested coming out early chy will do
the Sanskrit it's really nice to have
the Sanskrit in your mind uh if you can
okay
I think that's it do the do the